# 麻辣鲜香烫 香气四溢
Spiciness, numbness, Umami, aroma and hot! All those flavors are bursting out.
# 各位网友朋友们 大家好
Hi everyone
# 今天是个特别的日子
It’s a special day today
# 老饭骨师父们不在了
All the masters are not at home
# 给师父们放个假
They deserve a small break
# 今天我们哥仨给大家呈现一道
And the three of us will teach you how to prepare
# 最好吃的家常菜
One of the most popular dishes for home kitchen
# 什么呢 水煮鱼
That is: water-boiled spicy fish
# 这些个料 看看这料 我照照这料
Look at all the ingredients
# 这个鱼咱们在家
It’s for home cooking
# 就选草鱼就可以
We are using grass carp today
# 把这鱼洗完之后
After cleaning the fish
# 如果表面水太多 擦一擦
Remember to wipe out the excess water
# 再保险一点还滑怎么办啊
If it’s still slippery, here’s a tip.
# 下边垫一块毛巾它就不滑了
Put a piece of cloth underneath to stop it from slippering
# 就做半条了
Half of it is enough
# 草鱼的刺全在这块呢
This is where all the bones are hidden
# 咱们给它片下去
We just need to slice it off
# 这刀真快
What a sharp knife
# 把下面刮一刮
Let’s clean the surface
# 刚才我师兄说了
We said just now
# 下边感觉滑
The fish is slippery because
# 因为它鱼表面有黏液
There is slime over its skin
# 把这黏液给刮掉
Let’s get rid of it with the knife
# 越大越好这水煮鱼
The larger the slices, the better
# 尤其在家里边吃 吃的过瘾
Especially when cooking at home, so satisfying
# 看到没有这么厚的片
See how thick it is?
# 这鱼咱们片好了
OK we are done with slicing
# 稍微来点盐
A little bit of salt
# 来半个蛋清就够了
Half of egg white
# 加点葱姜的
Spring onion, ginger
# 搁里边一样出水 一样
There are moistures coming out of it (这句我真不知道他们指的是什么)
# 来点水淀粉
Here, some starch mixed with water
# 直接往里倒点黄酒
Then we add some yellow Chinese rice wine
# 水淀粉
About that starch
# 刚才这个淀粉是水淀粉
We mixed it with some water
# 主要是生粉
It was potato or corn starch
# 鱼肉大概腌个十到二十分钟
We need to marinate it for about 10-20 minutes
# 我这个水煮鱼叫妙辣水煮鱼
I call this dish Fish Boiled with “Special” Spicy Soup
# 跟油做的水煮鱼还不一样
It’s different from the common recipes
# 妙辣体现在哪你看
What’s so “special”
# 这么多的调料 这就叫妙辣
Well, look at all these spices, that’s the special part.
# 妙由百味生
Special because of the complex flavor.
# 第一步热锅凉油
First, heat up the wok and pour in some oil
# 这油里边咱们稍微给它
In addition to that
# 加一点猪油 这样更香
Let’s put some pork fat in it to intensify the aroma.
# 把葱姜蒜给它煸香
Fry the spring onion, ginger and garlic
# 豆瓣酱 郫县豆瓣
Doubanjiang (Sichuan chili bean paste)
# 三成热 慢慢把这香味
Cook it slowly on low heat
# 都得给浸泡出来
And let it release all the aroma
# 然后下边我们就依次放入
Now, we need the spices
# 八角 三粒 豆蔻
Star anise, three of it, nutmeg.
# 都放里了
In there
# 十五粒小茴香
About fifteen fennel seeds
# 先放硬的东西
The hard spices will go in first
# 为什么先放硬的原材料
Why?
# 硬的原材料禁熬
Because they can handle more cooking time
# 丁香 草果
Cloves, tsao-ko
# 小茴香两克 草果一个
2 grams of fennel seeds, one tsao-ko
# 丁香二十粒
20 cloves
# 陈皮掰点儿就行 香叶两片
A bit of dried mandarin peel, two bay leaves
# 桂皮稍微掰点就够
A bit of cinnamon
# 白芷 三片
baizhi (Angelica dahurica), three pieces
# 好 这会熬得差不多了
Alright we are almost done with the frying
# 咱们该放什么呢 辣椒
What’s next? Chili pepers
# 这个是普通辣椒
We have here the common dried chili peppers
# 整颗放就行 有十五个
We need about 15 pieces.
# 辣椒王 咱们少放一点
Now, the really spicy “Chili King”, let’s not put too much of it.
# 普通的辣椒提香
So the common ones are for the aroma
# 辣椒王是增加辣度厚度
While the “Chili King” is for an intensive spiciness.
# 加醋吗 不加
Vinegar? No not today.
# 师兄咱们哥仨就不加了
We really don’t need to argue about that between us
# 怎么着也得斗起来了
Not like the masters.
# 慢慢加热水 先来一勺
Let’s pour in the hot water slowly. Bit by bit.
# 需要加几次啊
How much do we need?
# 咱们把这小盆都倒进去就行
This whole bowl.
# 这会就等着开了锅
Now, let’s wait until its boiling.
# 咱们给它煮一煮
And let it boil for a while
# 大约熬几分钟
A few minutes
# 大概熬个二十分钟
Maybe around 20 minutes
# 小火慢熬 好嘞
Keep it boiling on low heat
# 师兄咱们煮到一半的时候
After about 10 minutes
# 咱们加点原材料 加什么呢
We need to add more ingredients to it
# 一个是辣椒面
First the chili flakes
# 还有两种花椒
Then two types of Sichuan pepper
# 为什么说中间加
Why do we put them in in the middle of the boiling process?
# 这就是妙处所在
That’s the special part too.
# 因为你刚开始加的时候
If you add the chili flakes too early,
# 辣椒面就糊了
It might become soggy. (这里我觉得他说的糊应该是煮的时间太长了糊了？)
# 所以说中间加辣椒面 加一半
That’s why we add it half way during boiling.
# 花椒着油之后虽然说更香
Indeed the Sichuan peppers smells better after frying
# 但是把麻度和香度都减弱了
But frying also reduces the aroma and the numbing taste
# 有所衰减 中间放
That’s why we also only put them in during the boiling process.
# 网友朋友们
Dear friends
# 这个麻椒和花椒是两种概念
There are two different types of Sichuan peppers
# 花椒是增香
Huajiao is one used for its aroma
# 麻椒是增麻度和厚度
And Majiao is the one used to intensify the numbing taste
# 香度也够了
Alright it smells good already
# 咱们给它过过箩
Let’s pass it through the sieve
# 来吧师弟我扶着
I got it.
# 要配合的好
That requires some cooperation
# 有吹笛儿的有捏眼儿的
Good teamwork right there!
# 这会儿咱们汤熬好了
OK now the spicy soup is ready
# 鱼腌的也差不多了
Fish is marinated too.
# 这是小料 事先切好的
Here are some extra ingredients I prepared earlier
# 姜末 蒜末 小葱段儿
Ginger, garlic, spring onion
# 姜片儿 干葱 辣椒段
Ginger again, shallots, and dried chili pepper
# 青笋 大白菜 黑木耳
Celtuce, Chinese cabbage, black mushroom
# 莴笋好吃啊
I love celtuce
# 这水煮鱼啊
This is a fish dish
# 这里头这菜好 入味啊
But the vegetables in it are also delicious
# 有的在家说愿意把菜焯水
Some prefer to first cook the vegetables with boiling water.
# 但是我今天做我就不焯水了
I am not doing that today
# 直接炒先给它炒一遍
I will just stir fry it directly.
# 增加了锅气
It gives more “wok-hei”
# 稍微来点油 小干葱 辣椒段
A bit of oil, shallots in with dried chili pepper
# 这时候火关小一点
Let’s turn down the heat
# 稍微来点麻椒和花椒
A little bit of both types of Sichuan peppers
# 来一点豆瓣酱 小豆瓣
A little bit of Doubanjiang
# 这会儿把菜放进去
Vegetables in.
# 小锅翻的溜
Your pan flipping skills is pretty good!
# 稍微烹点刚才咱们熬那个汁
Pour a bit of the spicy soup in.
# 来点盐 来点糖
Salt, and sugar
# 这个里边为什么加点糖
Why do we need sugar?
# 辣的东西一定要加糖
Sugar goes well with spicy dishes
# 加糖才有复合味
It adds complicity to the flavor
# 如果不加糖是寡辣
Otherwise you only taste the spiciness.
# 这回菜熟的差不多了
OK the vegetables are cooked
# 咱们给它倒到碗里 垫底儿的菜
Let’s put them at the bottom of the bowl
# 刚才熬那汤 倒进去
Pour the spicy soup in the wok.
# 加盐 糖
Salt, sugar
# 这时候改小火
Cook it on low heat
# 打开了给它一片片往里下
Unfold the fish slices and put them in the soup one by one.
# 往往就是一起下了之后
You should not put all of them in at once.
# 都煮到一起了就 分开下
The slices will stick to each other. You must do it one by one.
# 你看这会儿这鱼片非常的饱满
See? The slices are nicely thick
# 鱼片的表面淀粉遇热会凝结
The starch around the fish will form a layer when heated
# 就像穿了一层衣服一样
It’s like wearing clothes
# 然后就保住了水分 锁住水分
It locks the moisture in the fish
# 适当的把火稍微加大
Now we can turn the heat up a bit.
# 大概煮个五分钟 三到五分钟
Let it boil for 3-5 minutes
# 稍微的晃一下 晃晃锅就行
Give it a little shake
# 稍微给来点淀粉 薄芡
A little bit of the starch to thicken the soup a bit
# 轻轻推
Just push it gently
# 师兄你看这大鱼片
Look at that large piece
# 最符合在家吃 过瘾
Perfect for family dinners, satisfying!
# 看这鱼片 特别的整
The slices are still in one piece.
# 水煮鱼最后一步就是呲油
Last step, we need to pour hot oil onto it.
# 又第三种辣椒 灯笼椒
This is the third type of dried chili peppers, the bell peppers.
# 主要是增香
Used mainly for its aroma.
# 灯笼椒要焯遍水
We need to boil it first
# 为什么要焯遍水 我给大家讲
Why do we do that?
# 所有的辣椒你在炸之前
You need to boil the dried chilies peppers
# 都要焯遍水
Before frying them
# 因为不焯水的话
Otherwise
# 它会糊的很快 糊就苦了
They will get burned very easily and become bitter.
# 花椒 焯一下水
We boil some Sichuan pepper too
# 蒜末 姜末
Garlic and ginger
# 呲油的时候
About the hot oil
# 我们给它来点辣椒油
We need some chili oil too
# 辣椒油需要提前熬
We prepared the chili oil in advance
# 用什么呢
How?
# 辣椒 色拉油 猪油 花椒
We used dried chili pepper, cooking oil, pork fat, Sichuan pepper
# 这些香料熬制的红辣椒油
To make this red chili oil.
# 在这儿就不现熬了
We did it in advance.
# 辣椒油加点色拉油
Chili oil mixed with cooking oil
# 油温不要太高的时候
When the oil temperature is not too high yet
# 就把这些放进去
Let’s put the spices in
# 经过水焯的花椒辣椒
The boiled chili pepper and Sichuan pepper
# 味道会更香
Give a stronger aroma
# 而且它会禁熬
And you can cook them longer in the oil
# 原料在油炸过程当中会脱水
The spices will dehydrate in hot oil
# 如果水少它会快速脱水
If you don’t boil them beforehand, they will dry out too quickly
# 没有把它本身的味道
And they might get burned
# 释放到油当中就变色了
Before they can release all their flavors into the oil
# 隋师兄专业的术语太棒了
Chef Sui is teaching us all the terminologies.
# 辣椒不能等到糊了再往外捞
Take them out before they are burned
# 关键时刻
The critical moment is here.
# 漂亮
Beautiful
# 辣椒恰到好处
The chili peppers are fried perfectly
# 糊与未糊之间
Colored but not burned.
# 麻辣鲜香烫
Spiciness, numbness, Umami, aroma and hot!
# 香气四溢
All those flavors are bursting out.
# 最后我们就着这个热劲儿
Lastly, while it’s still hot
# 再把葱花放进去
Let’s put the spring onions in
# 点睛之笔 齐活
The final touch, and it’s done!
# 师兄上次你也做了一次
You made this dish before
# 正好给我点评点评 妙辣
So you should comment on my “special” version of this dish.
# 妙辣水煮鱼
It is quite special
# 区别于以往我吃过的水煮鱼
Different from what I am used to
# 妙 妙在哪里
What’s so special?
# 妙在它里面的鱼片的复合味
Well, the complex flavor in the fish
# 鱼片的口感
The texture of the fish
# 包括下边的垫菜
The vegetables underneath
# 上面的呲的这些料
As well as everything on top
# 都是非常妙
They are all very special.
# 融合得非常好
Very harmonious.
# 地道
Spot-on!
# 绝了
Amazing.
# “我是大爷”这句开始时间：
# 00:08:23,01